<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certain letters, evidencing the Kings stedfastness in the Protestant religion: sent from the Princess of Turenne, and the ministers of Charenton, to some persons of quality in London.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78472</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1702</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1079_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16902</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860111</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860111</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112218</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78472)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112218)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 161:E1079[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certain letters, evidencing the Kings stedfastness in the Protestant religion: sent from the Princess of Turenne, and the ministers of Charenton, to some persons of quality in London.</title>
                  <author>Turenne, Anne de La Tour d'Auvergne, Vicomtesse de.</author>
                  <author>Gaches, Raymond, d. 1668.</author>
                  <author>Daillé, Jean, 1594-1670.</author>
                  <author>Drelincourt, Charles, 1595-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Thomas Newcomb for Gabriel Bedell, and Thomas Collins, and are to be sold at their shop at the Middle Temple gate in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Letters in French and English, and in Latin and English, in parallel columns.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "may 11th".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery (Early English books) and in the British Library (Thomason tracts).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestants --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112218:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>CERTAIN</hi> LETTERS EVIDENCING THE KINGS STEDFASTNESS IN THE Proteſtant Religion: SENT From the Princeſs of <hi>Turenne,</hi> and the Miniſters of <hi>Charenton,</hi> to ſome Perſons of Quality in LONDON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Newcomb</hi> for <hi>Gabriel Bedell,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Collins,</hi> and are to be ſold at their Shop at the Middle Temple gate in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:112218:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112218:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>SUch hath been the unwearied malice of the enemies of our peace, that when by open force they could no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger rationally hope to hinder a ſettlement on the ſure foundations of Righteouſneſs and Juſtice, They have made lies their refuge; and laboured to poiſon the affections of the good people of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe eyes the Lord hath now open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſee what is moſt conducing to their peace. For though it hath pleaſed God by a ſeries of wonderful and gratious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences to break the ſeveral yokes of Tyrannie under which the Nation groan'd, though by the courage and wiſdom of the Noble Lord General <hi>Monck,</hi> the fears of good men are ſecured from any further violences, and their hopes raiſed to enjoy their antient liberties by free Parliaments, yet thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natique ſpirits ceaſe not to undermine our hopes, and to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to involve us into new confuſions: It is a laſting ſettlement which they fear, and therefore they bend their malice againſt <hi>Him</hi> whom the body of the People look upon as the Corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone (under God) of that ſettlement. His Wiſdom, His Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and His other eminent Vertues are ſo univerſally known at home and abroad, they are ſo improved in the ſchool of affliction, which hath procured him ſo many eye-witneſſes of thoſe graces, even perſons of the greateſt quality beyond Sea
<pb facs="tcp:112218:3"/> (who otherwiſe ſhould only have known them by fame.) That his enemies had no hope to prevail by leſſening him as to thoſe endowments. But having driven him from the places where the reformed Religion is openly profeſt, they have baſely ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him of late, as if he had left the Profeſsion of that Faith of which he was born to be the Defender. This hath engaged many very conſiderable perſons beyond the Sea to bear witneſs to the Truth, and to vindicate ſo clear and unqueſtionable an innocence from that falſe and baſe calumnie. Divers Letters have been written, four are here preſented to publick view: The firſt is from the Princeſs of <hi>Turenne,</hi> Wife to one of the greateſt Captains that <hi>Europe</hi> hath ſeen in this Age, who for the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſervices done to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> is of late juſtly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to be Marſhal-General of that kingdom, and continues conſtant in the reformed Religion. The Letter it ſelf ſpeaks ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently both the Wiſdom and Piety of that Princeſs, ſhe is the Grandchild of the famous Duke and Marſhall <hi>de la Force,</hi> whoſe Family hath always continued zealouſly Proteſtants, and her teſtimonie is above exception, for ſhe ſpeaks from her own particular knowledge. The Original is in the hands of a Noble Lady her Couſin Germane here in <hi>London,</hi> to whom it was written, and hath been ſeen by many.</p>
            <p>The other Letters are from three Miniſters of the reformed Church at <hi>Charenton</hi> near <hi>Paris,</hi> men ſo famous for their learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Writings, that their names make them ſufficiently known:
<pb facs="tcp:112218:3"/> all of them are certainly moſt impartial witneſſes, they cannot be preſumed to be byaſſed by any private intereſt, they are not born his Subjects whoſe innocencie they defend: It is only for the Truth that they ingage, and for the concerns of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, being deeply ſenſible how much its Honor and Safety depends on the preſent tranſactions here, which they ſo fully expreſs, that the Reader ſhall be no longer detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the following Letters.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:112218:4"/>
            <div xml:lang="fre" type="version">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:112218:4"/>
               <head>UNE LETTRE DE <hi>S. A. MADAME</hi> De TURENNE, A Madamoiſelle <hi>De CASTELNA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T,</hi> A LONDRES.</head>
               <p>SI vous n'eſteé accouſtumée de long temps, ma chere Couſine, à ſupporter &amp; à par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donner ma pareſſe, je ſerors en peine du jugement que vous faites de mon ſilence, &amp; de ce que j'ay tant differe à repondre a la derniere lettre que j'ay re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceve de vous, Mats ſi voſtre facilite me met à couvert des reproches que vous auries droit de me faire, elle ne me garentit pas de ceux que je me dois faire a moy meſme lors que je neglige de vous donner
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112218:5"/> les marques qui ſont en ma pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſance, de la tendreſſe que jay pour vous; Il eſt vray que j'aurois plus d'empreſſement à vous en donner des prevues eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentielles &amp; utiles que je n'en ay a vous en faire voir ces foi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles aſſeurances: &amp; je vous aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ma chere Couſine, que les occaſions m'en ſeront touſiours fort cheres, &amp; que je les em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braſſeray de bon coeur toutes les fois que je le pourray, Jay pourtant à vous faire une plainte de vous meſme, que vous m'avéz encore eſcrit a vec ceremonie, &amp; que vous n'avéz pas voulu ſuiure cette métode icy qui eſt beaucoup plus libre &amp; plus commode, &amp; ſans men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir c'eſt ce qui à encore un peu aydé a ma pareſſe car je ſuis ſi diſcoutumeé d'eſcrire en forme &amp; ſur tout aux gens que j'ayme cordialement, qui je
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112218:5"/> ne ſcay come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t m'y prendre et je craignois qu'ily ait trop d'in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilité apres tous les complime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts qui vous me faites d'en uſer avec tant de liberté. En fin pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant jay creu Madamoiſelle ma chere Couſine, que cela ne ſeroit pas capable de vous faire ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonner que je manquaſſe à join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre a l'affection qui j'ay pour vous, tous les ſentemens d'hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neur &amp; de conſideration qui vous ſont deu, &amp; à quoy je ſuis plus particulierement obligeé qu'une autre et par la proximité &amp; par quantité d'autres raiſons. Etſi pourquoy je me ſuis fermee a continuer den uſer de cette ſorte dans la reſolution de vous vainere &amp; de vous obliger d'én faire de meſme autrement ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voue que je prendrois ce refus pour un certein compliment qui marqueroit plus de civilite que d'amitie, &amp; pour une eſpece de renoncement au commerce je
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112218:6"/> veux done atendre de vous chere Couſine, une Lettre fort tendre &amp; peu ceremonieuſe &amp; je vous les demande de cette ſorte &amp; de recevoir celle cy de la meſme affection qu'elle vous eſt écrite. Il me tarde fort que nous ayons la ſatisfaction de vous revoir en ce pays cy, vous au és bien veu desja des revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions en celuy ou vous eſtes, &amp; quelque deſir que je ſouhaite de tout mon coeur que vous y puiſsiés encore voir celle que l'eſtat preſent des affaires nous donne lieu de pouvoir bien toſt eſperer, &amp; que tous les gens de bien deſirent avec une extreme paſsion, qui eſt le retour du Roy dans ſon premier éclat &amp; ſa pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miere authorite jay touſiours ſouhaite avec grande paſsion le retabliſsement de ce Prince par diverſes conſiderations &amp; par le deſir qu'il me ſemble que cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112218:6"/> doit avoir que les choſes ſe faſent dans la juſtice, &amp; par l'horreur du crime commis ſur la perſonne du Roy ſon pere qui a depuis attiré de ſi terribles jugemens ſur ces nations, &amp; vne li effroyable confuſion parmy les Egliſes que Dieu y auoit recueillies &amp; quil y auoit fait fleurir avec tant d'eclat et de pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reté, qu'on ne peut s'empeſcher de pleurer ſur leurs ruines auſsi a mereme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t qu' <hi>Edras, Nehemie,</hi> &amp; <hi>Daniel</hi> ſur celles de <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> juſqu' à ce quil ait pleu au Sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gneur de nous ex aucer &amp; de les retablir, j'avoue que je ne crois point que ce peche ſe puiſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier, ny cet interdit eſtre oſté du milieu d'eux que par le retabliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſement de leur legitime &amp; So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerain Seigneur &amp; en luy ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t la puiſſance qu'il à receue de Dieu &amp; qui depuis long temps on uſurpe ſur luy, le meſme qui nous ordonne de rendre à Dieu
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112218:7"/> ce qui appartient a Dieu, nous comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de auſsi de rendre a Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar ce qui appartient a Cezar, de ſorte que je crois que celuy qui voudroit le contenter dun de ces deux devoirs, &amp; ſeparer ainſy les choſes qui Dieu a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jointes, ne ſatisferoit a aucun, &amp; un ſeruice ainſy es-tropié ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roit bien moins acceptable par mi les Chriſtiens, que neſtoit une offrande mutilee parmi les Juifs. Ces conſiderations me font ſouhaiter avec grande paſsion que Dieu inſpire ces na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions a faire leur devoir, mais javoue que je redouble mes voeux &amp; mon ardeur lors qui j'oy dire que ceux qui gouver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent a preſent ne ſont plus tous ces Sectaires, mais des gens de noſtre profeſsion. Ils ont eu le malheur d'eſtre calomnies par le; adverſaires comme complices de la mort de leur Souverain, &amp; cette infame acuſation ſemble
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112218:7"/> avoir noircy tous leurs freres; lové ſoit le Dieu de miſericorde qui leur preſente une ſi belle oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion de s'en lauer &amp; d'en ofter la reproche d'une ſi ſainte pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion qu'eſt la noſtre, de que nous nous ſommes tous jours va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tés qu' elle auoit cet auantage par deſſus toutes les autres d'ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prendre mieux qu' aucun ce que l'ondoit aux Souverains &amp; de ne permettre ſous aucun pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texte qu'on ſe diſpenſant du ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment de fidelité qu' on leur au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roit preſté, j'ay une telle impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence d'apprendre qu' on l'ait re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablie en honneur de ce coſté la par une action ſi juſte &amp; ſi belle, que je ne vous puis dire avec combien d'affection je le de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manday a Dieu le jour du juſne que nous celebraſmes le ſemain de Paſque a <hi>Charenton:</hi> &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bien je luy demande tous les jours, &amp; je crois quil n'y a guere de gens qui s'affectionent à la
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112218:8"/> Paix de <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> qui ne luy facent cette priere, &amp; je vois tous ceux de noſtre profeſsion en ce Royaune out plus ce deſir que jamais, ſoit que Dieu leur inſpire ce mouvement dans le temps qu'il veut faire ſon oeuvre de l'en prier plus inſtament, comme il ſe plaiſt ſouuent a faire rencontrer les voeux de ſes enfans avec les decrets de ſa pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vidence, ſoit que l'on ait mieux remarqué depuis quelque temps des effets de la pieté du Roy d' <hi>Angleterre</hi> qui fait que l'on ſintereſſe plus ſenſiblement a ce qui le touche. Pour moy j'avoue que j'en fus tres ſatisfaite quand j'eu l'honeur de luy faire la reverance la derniere fois qu'il a paſſe en ce pais, l ayant ouy parler auce tant de tes moignages de piete j'en fus tres edifiée, Il voulut auſsi donner cette marque de ſa communion avec nos Egliſes d'aller au
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112218:8"/> preſche a la <hi>Rochel</hi> &amp; <hi>Rouen</hi> en paſſant, &amp; ſil euſt ſejourné icy nons euſsions eu l'honeur de le voir à <hi>Charenton,</hi> il ne ſe peut rien ajouſter a la regulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>té qu'a ce Prince a aſsiſter tous les jours aux exercices de piete qui ſe font ches luy ſoir &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin; en fin je loue Dieu de ce que lon void ſur luy des marques de l'Election de Diu &amp; j'eſpere qui'l ſe ſervira de luy pour reta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blir ce que nous avous veu au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre fois auec tant de plaiſir en ſes Etats, &amp; que ſes Sujets au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ront lieu de benir le Seigneur de leur auoir mis au coeur de ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre a leur Roy ſa couronne, mais auſsi belle qu'il l'eut ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mais, &amp; ſans la vouloir fleſtrir &amp; gaſter en la luy mettant ſur la teſte. Je prie Dieu de tout mon coeur qu'il leur en face la grace, &amp; je l'ay ſi fort au coeur qui je me laiſſe aller à vous en faire une longue lettre qui a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lair
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112218:9"/> d'un petit volume, mais ceſt qui je crois, chere couſine, que comme vous eſtes ſur les lieux, il eſt du devoir de contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buer tous jours autant que l'on peut a donner cette pensée a ceux qui ne l'auroient pas, &amp; que chacun doit avoir l'ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dapporter ſa petite pierre a cet excellent ouvrage. Comme je ſouhaite fort que ceux a qui je m'intereſſe s'employe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aux cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes bonnes je ſerois rauye que Madame voſtre belle ſoeur &amp; vous peuſsiés contribuer quel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que choſe a cecy, obliges moy je vous ſupplie de I'aſſeurer de mon ſervice tres humble &amp; de me croire tout a vous</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Ox. Caumont.</signed>
                  <dateline>Cemardy <date>6. Avril 1660.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:112218:4"/>
               <head>A LETTER from the <hi>PRINCESS</hi> of <hi>TURENNE</hi> To a Noble Lady her Couſin German, Madam de <hi>Caſtelnaut;</hi> at LONDON.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Dear Couſin,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF you had not been for a long time accuſtomed to bear with, and to pardon my lazineſs, I ſhould be in pain for the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you might make of my ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and that I have delayed ſo long to anſwer the laſt Letter I received from you: But if your goodneſs protects me from the reproaches which you have reaſon to charge me with, it does not ſecure me from thoſe which I ought to lay to my own charge, when I neglect to give you ſuch
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112218:5"/> teſtimonies as I am able of the tenderneſs I have for you. It is true that I ſhall be more earneſt to give you real and uſeful proofs of it, then I am to let you ſee theſe weak aſſurances; and you may be confident, my dear Couſin, that I ſhall ever cheriſh ſuch opportunities, and embrace them with all my heart as often as I am able. Yet I muſt complain of you to your ſelf, becauſe you have again written to me with ceremonie, and did not follow this method which is more frank and more convenient; and truly this was the thing which did contribute to my laſineſs; for I am ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with formall wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, eſpecially to thoſe I love ſo heartily, that I know not how to ſet my ſelf to it, and I was afraid that it would be too un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civil to uſe ſuch freedome after
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112218:5"/> all thoſe complements you gave me; Yet at laſt, Madam my dear Couſin, I thought this ſhould not make you ſuſpect that I could fail to join to that affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction I have for you, all thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments of honour and reſpect which are due to you, and to which I am more particularly obleiged then another, both by nearneſs in bloud, and by many other reaſons: therefore I am fixed to continue in this way in the reſolution to overcome you, and to oblige you to do ſo too; otherwiſe, I do declare, that I ſhall take a refuſall for ſuch a complement as witneſſes more civility then friendſhip, and for a kind of renouncing of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce. I will therefore, Dear Couſin, expect a very kinde Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with little Ceremonie, ſuch a one I doe deſire, and that you would receive this with the ſame affection wherewith I do write
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112218:6"/> it. I long much for the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to ſee you again in this Countrey, you have already ſeen many revolutions in that where you are; and whatever my long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be for your return, I do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow it, That I wiſh with all my heart you may yet ſee there that change, which the preſent condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of affairs gives us reaſon to hope very ſhortly, and which all good men deſire with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream paſsion: that is, <hi>The KINGS return into his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Luſtre and Authoritie.</hi> I have ever wiſhed with great paſsion the re-eſtabliſhement of that Prince for divers reaſons, both for the deſire which I think every one ought to have, that things be done according to Juſtice, and for the horror of the crime committed upon the perſon of the King his father, which hath ſince drawn down ſuch ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible judgments on thoſe nations,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112218:6"/> and ſo fearful confuſions in thoſe Churches, which God had gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there, and which he had made flouriſh with ſo much lustre and purity, that one cannot forbear to weep over their ruine as bitterly as <hi>Ezra, Nehemiah,</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> did over that of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> untill it may pleaſe the Lord to hear us &amp; ſettle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I profeſs I cannot believe that that ſin can be expiat, nor the interdit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from among them, but by the re-eſtabliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Soveraign Lord, and by the rendring to him, that power which he received from God, and which for ſo long a time hath been uſurped over him. The ſame who commands to give God the things which are Gods, commands us alſo to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars: So that I believe that he who would content himſelf with one of theſe two duties, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112218:7"/> ſo ſeparate the things which God hath joined, ſhould ſatisfie weither, and that ſo lame a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice ſhould be leſs acceptable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians then a lame of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering was among the Jews. Theſe conſiderations make me wiſh with great paſsion that God would inſpire thoſe Nations to do their dutie; but I do avow it, that I double my prayers and my zeal when I hear that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Governours are no more thoſe ſectaries, but men of our profeſsion. They have had the misfortune to be ſlandered by the adverſaries, as acceſſarie to the death of their Soveraign, and that infamous accuſation ſeems to have blackt all their brethren. Bleſſed be the God of mercie who preſents to them ſo fair an occaſion to clear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to remove that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach from ſo holy a profeſsion as ours is, which we have ever
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112218:7"/> bragged to have this advantage above all others, in that it did teach us better then any other that which we owe to Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns, and did not permit that men ſhould under any pretext whatſoever diſpenſe themſelves of the Oath of Fidelity which they have taken. I have ſo great an impatiencie to hear that they have there ſo reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht it by ſo juſt and ſo lovely an action, that I cannot tell you with how much affection I begg'd it of God on the Faſt day which we kept at <hi>Charenton</hi> laſt Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter week, and how earneſtly I do beg it every day: And I believe there be few lovers of the Peace of Jeruſalem who make not the ſame prayer; and I ſee that all thoſe of our profeſsion in this kingdom are more earneſt in this then ever: Whether it be that God inſpires this moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to pray more earneſtly in a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112218:8"/> time when he will doe his work (as he is often pleaſed to make the prayers of his children meet with the decrees of his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence) or whether they have taken more notice of late of the <hi>effects of the Piety of the KING of England,</hi> which makes them intereſs themſelves more ſenſibly in his concerns. For my own part I profeſs it, that I was exceedingly ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied when I had the honour to pay my reſpects to him the laſt time he paſt through this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, having heard him ſpeak with ſo great teſtimonies of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that I was extreamly edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. He was alſo pleaſed to give this mark of his communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with our Churches as to go to Sermon at <hi>Rochell</hi> and at <hi>Rouen</hi> in his paſſage; and if he had ſtayed here, we had had the honour to have ſeen him at <hi>Charenton.</hi> There can no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112218:8"/> be added to the regularity which this Prince keeps in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting dayly at thoſe exerciſes of Piety which are kept mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and evening in his family: <hi>In a word I bleſs God becauſe the marks of God's Election are ſeen in Him:</hi> and <hi>I</hi> hope God will uſe his ſervice for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhing what we have before ſeen with ſo much pleaſure in his Dominions, and that his Subjects will have cauſe to bleſs the Lord for putting it into their hearts, to render to their King His Crown, and as fair as ever he had it, and without ſpoiling or defacing it in ſetting it on his head; I pray God with all my heart that he may give them this Grace, and I do ſo lay it to heart, that I take the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to write you a long Letter of it, which looks like a little vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume. But it is, dear Couſin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I beleeve that as you are on
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112218:9"/> the place, it is a point of duty to contribute always what one can to infuſe theſe thoughts in ſuch as have them not, and that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ought to be ambitious to bring their little ſtone toward that excellent work. As I do deſire very much that thoſe in whom I am concerned may em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy themſelves toward what is excellent, I ſhall be very glad that my Lady your Siſter in Law, and you might contribute ſomwhat to this; Obliege me by aſſuring her of my moſt humble ſervice, and by beleeving me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours Ox Caumont</signed>
                  <dateline>Tueſday <date>6. of <hi>April</hi> New stile 1660.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="fre" type="version">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:112218:9"/>
               <head>UNE LETTRE <hi>De Monſieur DAILLE a Monſieur LE ROY.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Monſieur,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>UN de mes a mis m'ayant prie depuis peu de luy faire venir un exemplaire de la grand Bible de <hi>Londres,</hi> je me ſuis ſouvenu que vous nous offrites I' hyver paſſé, a Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Duret</hi> et a moy, de nous en faire avoir une pour cinquante eſcus; de ſorte que j' ay creu que je ne pouvois mieux m'a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſer qu'àvous, dans cette rencontre, afin de ſervir mon amy, &amp; jéſpere que vous ne me refuſerés pas la grace que je vous demande de me faire ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voir, ſi vous eſtes encore en pouvoir de nous tenir promeſſe &amp; de m'envoyer ce liure au pris
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:112218:10"/> que vous nous avés dit: Au reſte je ne puis m'empeſcher de me rejouir icy avec vous des heureuſes nouvelles qui nous vienent du lieu oùvous eſtes, &amp; qui nous aprenent que les deſirs de tous les peuples y ſemblent rapeller, d'une commune voix, leur Roy naturel &amp; legitime. Outre que la genoroſité &amp; I'é<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quité meſme nous obligent à ſouhaiter que ce Prince rentre dans ſon Royaume &amp; dans ſon Patrimoine, dont il a eſté in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtement depouillé, nous le de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vons encore deſirer pour I'hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neur de noſtre Religion, qui nous doit eſtre plus cher que tout autre intereſt. Car lors que nos adverſaires la voulurent charger autrefois du blaſme de la mort du feu Roy <hi>d'Angle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terre,</hi> vous ſavés que nous ſeumes fort bien nous deffendre de ce reproche, en le rejetta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t tout
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112218:10"/> entier ſur les Sectaires, qui en ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect eſtoient ſeules coupables de cet horrible crime: Mais au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jourd'huy nous ne ſommes plus dans les meſmes termes, puisque les choſes ont changé de face, le Sectairiſme ayant perdu ſon credit, ou du moins eſtant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chû de la puiſſance Souveraine, qui eſtoit en ſes mains, &amp; au con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taire le parti Presbyterien, qui eſt le noſtre, eſtant celuy qui gouverne preſentement en <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleterre:</hi> De maniere que s'il laiſſe échaper la belle occaſion que Dieu ſemble luy ouvrir, de retablir S. M. <hi>Britanique</hi> dans ſes Eſtats, &amp; le faire remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſur le troſne de ſes Anceſtres, il eſt tout clair qu'il n'y aura plus lieu de s'excuſer ſur les Sectaires, ny de laver noſtre ſainte Religion, de cette tache, dont, par la grace de Dieu, elle s'eſt tousjours conſervée pure &amp;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112218:11"/> nette juſques à preſent: Je ſcay bien que l'on fact courir de mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vais bruits de la Religion de ce Prince, &amp; je ne doute point qu'il n'y ait des gens à <hi>Londres</hi> auſsi bien qu'à <hi>Paris,</hi> qui taſchent de perſuader au monde, qu'il à quitté noſtre Communion pour embraſſer celle de <hi>Rome.</hi> Mais qui pourroit croire une choſe qui eſt ſi contraire à toute vray ſemblance? Il ne nous paroiſt rien de cela, au contraire, nous ſcavons que quoique ce Prince ait eſte obligé par l'Eſtat de ſa condition preſente, à viure quel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que fois dans des lieur où l'exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cice de noſtre Religion n'eſt pas permis, neantmoins il a tousjours eu aupres de ſa per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonne, ſes Chapelains, qui ne ſont rien moins que Papiſtes, &amp; qui par tout ont fact reglement en ſa preſence, les prieres &amp; les autres parties du ſervice divin.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112218:11"/> De plus tout <hi>Paris</hi> &amp; toute la terre a ſeu, la colere &amp; la juſte indignation qu'il teſmoigna lors qu'il aprit les efforts qu'on avoit employés, quoy qu'inutilement pour faire revolter le Duc de <hi>Glocester;</hi> &amp; ſi d'un coſté ce jeune Prince fit alors admirer ſa Pieté &amp; ſa Conſtance, par la firme reſiſtance qu'il opoſa dans une age ſi tendre, à une ſi vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lante &amp; ſi dangereuſe perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, auſsi d'autre part ce qu'il ſe retira auprés du Roy ſon fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, &amp; qu'il y chercha un aſyle à ſa Religion, eſt une marque bien certaine, que le Roy n'a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voit pas quitté cette Religion, puis que ſi cela euſi eſté, le Duc de <hi>Gloceſter</hi> au lieu d'un Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecteur euſi trouve en luy un ennemy, &amp; la perte de ſa con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience où il en cherchoit la ſeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reté, &amp; où il la rencontra en effet. On objecte à cela que
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112218:12"/> durant tout le temps que S. M. <hi>Britanique</hi> a paſſé à la Cour de <hi>France,</hi> elle ne s'eſt jamais trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vée dans les aſſembleés religieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes de ceux de noſtre communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; qu' entre autres, elle n'eſt pas venue une ſeule fois à <hi>Charenton,</hi> aux jours de nos ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercices. Mais quoy que cela puiſſe peut eſtre ſembler d'abord etrange à ceux qui n'en ſcavent pas la raiſon, neantmoins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me nous en ſommes mieux in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formez que perſonne, nous pouvons luy rendre teſmoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnage, que la Religion n'en a point eſté cauſe, &amp; qu'il n'en a eſte empeſche que par des con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations de Politique et de Prudence, qui ſont, peut eſtre, particulieres à noſtre Egliſe; et pour preuve de cela, c'eſt que quand le Roy d' <hi>Angleterre</hi> a eſte hors de <hi>Paris,</hi> il n'a point fait difficulte d'aller au preſche
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:112218:12"/> dans les Temples de nos freres, comme par exemple à <hi>Caën,</hi> &amp; en quelques autres villes. Et en <hi>Holande</hi> tout de meſme, il a eſte ouir diverſes fois les predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations du celebre M. <hi>Morus,</hi> qui eſt à preſent noſtre Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legue.</p>
               <p>Ainſy, Monſieur, il eſt plus clair que le jour, que tout ce que l'on a dit juſqu'icy de ſon chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement de Religion, eſt vne pure calomnie, ſemée par l'arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice de ſes ennemis, pour le de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crier dans l'eſprit de ſes Sujets, et pour aliener de luy leurs affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; leur bonne volonte, &amp; enfin pour rompre l'effet des juſtes voeux, qu'ils forment au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jourdhuy pour ſon heureux re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour en <hi>Angleterre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Dieu vueille les exaucer, par ſa juſtice toute puiſſante, &amp; comme c'eſt luy qui a inſpire ces bons deſſeins dans le coeur de
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112218:13"/> ſon peuple, &amp; qui ſemble diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer toutes choſes à leur accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſſement, qu'il luy plaiſe benir la ſuite de cet ouvrage, &amp; le fair reuſsir a ſa glorie &amp; a celle de ſon oint, &amp; ſur tout à l'edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation de ſon Egliſe; je l'en prie de toute mon ame, &amp; vous recomande particulierement à ſa grace, comme eſtant.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Monſieur <hi>Votre tres humble ſerviteur,</hi> DAILLE.</signed>
                  <dateline>A PARIS <date>7 Avril 1660.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:112218:9"/>
               <head>A LETTER Of Monſieur DAILLE to Monſieur LE ROY.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>ONe of my Friends ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving deſired me a little while ſince, to ſend him a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of the great Bible Printed at <hi>London,</hi> I remembred, that the laſt Winter you propoſed to ſend one to Monſieur <hi>Duret,</hi> &amp; myſelf, for fifty Crowns; ſo that I believed, that in this occaſion I could not make an Addreſs to any with more conveniency then to you, that my friend might be provided; and I hope you will grant me the favor which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of you, to inform me, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you can at preſent perform your promiſe, and ſend me this Book for the price which you
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:112218:10"/> formerly expreſt. Moreover, I cannot but rejoyce with you for the happy news which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to us from the place where you are; whereby we are infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal deſire of the people, ſeems with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon voice to recal their Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Lawful King. Beſides that generoſity and equity its ſelf obliges us to wiſh, that this Prince may return into his own Kingdom and Inheritance, of which he hath been unjuſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived; we ought alſo to deſire it for the honor of our Religion, which ſhould be more dear to us, then any other intereſt: For when our Adverſaries formerly would charge the blame of the death of the late King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> on our Religion, you know we could very well guard our ſelvs from this reproach, by caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it intirely upon the Sectaries,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112218:10"/> who indeed were onely guilty of that horrible crime. But at preſent we do not ſtand upon the ſame terms, ſince there is ſuch a chance of affairs; the Sectarians having lost their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, or at least being faln from that ſoveraign Power which they had graſpt; and on the contrary the Presbyterian par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which is ours, now governing in <hi>England:</hi> So that if they let ſlip the fair opportunity which God ſeemes to open to them for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhing of the King of Great <hi>Britain</hi> in his Dominion, and to re-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance him to the Throne of his Anceſtors, it is moſt apparent there will be no further ground to excuſe themſelves upon the Sectaries, nor to waſh our holy Religion from that ſpot, from which, by the Grace of God it hath always bin preſerved pure
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112218:11"/> and clean to this preſent. I well know there are diſperſed evil rumors concerning the Religion of this Prince, and I doubt not, but there are ſome perſons at <hi>London,</hi> as well as at <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> who endeavour to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the World, That he hath forſaken our Communion, to embrace that of <hi>Rome:</hi> But who can believe a thing that is ſo contrary to all probability? there is nothing of this appears to us: On the contrary we well know, That although this Prince hath been conſtrained by the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of his preſent condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to reſide ſometimes in pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where the Exerciſe of our Religion is not permitted, yet he hath always had his Chaplains near to him, who are nothing leſs then Papiſts, and who every where have regularly in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence prayed, and performed the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112218:11"/> other parts of Divine Service. Moreover, all <hi>Paris,</hi> and all the World, hath known the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and the just indignation which he expreſt, when he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the endeavors which have been uſed (though ineffective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) for the Apoſtacy of the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter:</hi> And if this young Prince rendred his Piety and Conſtancy admirable, by that firm reſiſtance which he oppoſed in ſo tender an age, to ſuch a violent and dangerous perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo alſo in that he retired to the King his Brother, and there ſought for a Sanctuary to his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, it is a very certain argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the King had not quitted that Religion; for if this had been true, the Duke of <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> had found him an enemy, instead of a Protector, and had ſuffered the loſs of his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, where he had ſought its ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112218:12"/> &amp; where he really found it. It is objected againſt this, that during the whole ſpace of time which the King of Great <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> paſt in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> he never came to our religious aſſemblies, and that amongst o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, he never came to <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renton</hi> in the days of our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. But although this may at firſt view appear ſtrange to thoſe who know not the reaſon of it; nevertheleſs, as we are better informed of this then any one, we can testifie that Religion was not the cauſe of it, and that he abſtained from coming upon po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick and prudential conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which may be peculiar to our Church: And the proof of this appears in that when the King of <hi>England</hi> hath been out of <hi>Paris,</hi> he hath willingly gone to Sermon in the Churches of our Brethren; as for inſtance, in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:112218:12"/> 
                  <hi>Caen,</hi> and ſome other Towns; and in <hi>Holland</hi> alſo, he hath ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times heard the Sermons of the famous Monſieur <hi>More,</hi> who at preſent is our Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>league.</p>
               <p>Thus, Sir, it is more clear then the day, That whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hath been reported till this time of the change of his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, is a meer calumny, ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by the artifice of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; for to vilifie him in the judgment of his Subjects, and to alienate their affections and good will from him; and finally to render fruitleſs the juſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers which they make at preſent for his happy return into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God grant their accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by his Almighty Juſtice, and as it is he who hath inſpired theſe good deſigns into the hearts of his people, and who ſeems to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112218:13"/> diſpoſe all things for the effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them. May it pleaſe him to bleſs what remains of this work, and to ſucceed it for his glory, and the honor of his Anointed; but eſpecially for the edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Church. For this, I pray to him with all my Soul, and recommend you particularly to his Grace, being,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  <signed> 
                     <hi>Your moſt humble Servant</hi>DAILLE.</signed>
                  <dateline>PARIS, <date>7 April. 1660.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:112218:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>VIRO CELEBERRIMO, ET PASTORI INTEGERRIMO</hi> Richardo Baxtero, <hi>Raimondus Gacheus Eccleſ. Ref. Pariſ. Paſtor. S. P. D.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ACcedo ad te, vir clariſſime, &amp; frater in Chriſto ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervantiſſime, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> de fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cie, neque de famâ notus, accedo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amen confidenter, quia te opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mè novi, &amp; de tua pietate mihi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lanè perſuaſum eſt. Legi nem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e relegi, miratus ſum docta <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>la parva fateor, ſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>olem ſpectes, ſed Deus bone! <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uàm pretioſa, quàm vero Chriſtianiſmi ſucco penitùs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbuta, quibus <hi>Britanniam</hi> tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m beâſti, &amp; quibus non omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ò <hi>Gallia</hi> noſtra caruit. Quis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utem vel unius paginae ſeriâ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ctione non protinus intelligat,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112218:14"/> te ſpiritus Dei aflatum ſenſiſſe, te infoelicibus hiſce temporibus oportunè ſuſcitatum, qui graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantem impietatem forti pecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, armis invictis aggrediaris &amp; compeſcas Nihil unquam, ſanctè profiteor, nihil nec à vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus Eccleſiae patribus, ut vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gò vocant, nec ab ultimi ſeculi doctoribus profectum vidi, &amp; elucubratum, quod pari ſucceſſu pietatem autoris ſpiret, ſimúl<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pietatem lectoris accendat: quae de vita aeternâ, de peccatorum converſione, de juſtificatione, (in quâ ſi nonnihil à via trita deflectas, facis tamen quantùm aſſequi potui, non ſinè ratione, non ſinè Scriptura) de Poedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſmo, de con ſcientiae tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in lucem emiſiſti, teſtantur luculentiſſimè, &amp; quae tua ſit eruditio, &amp; quis tuus pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis affectus. In talis, &amp; tanti viri ſinum, quis animi mei ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112218:14"/> &amp; anxias cogitationes vetet effundere, &amp; quae mens agitat ſuper luctuoſum Reip. veſtrae &amp; incertum ſtatum declarare? Certè non ego ſum <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; potiſſimùm in rerum veſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum conditionem adeò non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onui inſenſus, ut nefas duxerim, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vel de illis curioſius diſputare. Dicam ampliùs, de <hi>Britannia</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>non potui, non bene ſperare, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eâ enim &amp; fui, &amp; permaneo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiâ. plures ſibi Deum in <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glia</hi> ſervâſſe electos, plures pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati deditos, quàm in ull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> totius Chriſtianitatis regno vel olim floruerint, vel nunc comparare poſſint. De ſalute veſtra de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent &amp; fratres timidi, &amp; hoſtes tumidi, quaerant in incredulitate ſua, Quis dabit è Zion ſalutare Iſrael? Providebit Deus non decem illic, non mille juſti, ſed integrae piorum Myriades. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam ego quid loquatur Dom.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112218:15"/> Deus, quoniam loquetur pacem in plebem ſuam. Verùm quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doquidem ſummus ille mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biter, qui nullo mediorum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terventu, poteſt &amp; tenebras diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellere, &amp; Iucem revocare, non vult tamen (ut plurimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatè virtutem ſuam exerere; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus, vir reverende, ſtudia no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra, conſilia omnia conferre ad ſalutem <hi>Britanniae</hi> firmitèr ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliendam. Nutabit, opinor, in perpetuum illius ſtatus, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nec ad unius Imperium res to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta redeat. Ut varii gentium mores, varia ingenia, ità variae apudillos adminiſtrandae R eip. rationes; non eadem omnibus eſt mens. Ille populus <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratiam</hi> elegit, non aſſuetus, non aſſuefaciendus Monarchiae; iſte Monarchiam praetulerit, nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatis ſplendore captus, &amp; plebis inſaniam exoſus. <hi>Anglia</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra ab innumeris penè ſeculis
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:112218:15"/> Reges coluit, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aliam novi in toto urbe antiquiorem Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchiam: Idem Sol lucet ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diernis <hi>Britannis,</hi> eoſdem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluuntillis affectus hodiè, quos olim aëris temperies, Aſtrorum aſpectus, ſoli qualitas; Quis ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret igitur vel Democratiam vel Ariſtocratiam facilè obtinere poſſe in eâ regione, in quâ unius Imperiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tam altas radices egit? Mutavit tamen <hi>Anglia,</hi> inquiet aliquis, &amp; mutavit conſenſu, ut videbatur, unanimi regiminis formam, quis neget commodè fieri poſſe, quod iam factum eſt commodè. Duplex mihi ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petit reſponſio. Primò, quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram viciſſim, utrùm <hi>Britaniae</hi> foeliciter prorſus evenerit illa mutatio, profectò ſi tributa, &amp; vectigalia computentur, ea non duplicata ſolùm, ſed in immen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum ferè aucta. ſi religionis ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum perpendas, quae haereſeôn
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112218:16"/> colluvies! Quis Renteros, Quakeros, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſub R'ege nove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat? Secundò, Foelix fuerit <hi>Britannia,</hi> at certè ſub unius Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perio; quid nomen morer? Protector fuit ille unus, non Rex, aſſentior, unus tamen, nec artis dominandi ignarus, &amp; qui, in ſolvendis R eip. veſtrae publicis conventibus, non mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norem ſe rege praeſtitit; nec ab illius obitu, aut ſaltem poſt fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ejus ejectum quievit <hi>Anglia;</hi> continuae viciſſitudines; quem heri venerabamur, execramur hodiè; &amp; cui modò fidelitatis jusjurandum dedimus, eum mox diris devovemus. Siccine ſemper fluctuabit nobiliſſima illa Inſularum Regina? ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ulla advolabit Alcion, quae ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re veſtrum tranquillet? Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem vereor) ut pacem unquam exploratam habeatis, vel contra domeſticos tumultus, vel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112218:16"/> hoſtium externorum moli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina, donec ſolium Avitum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiat tandem Ille, tot Regum Nepos, qui certè hereditario ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Regis <hi>Britanniae</hi> titulum paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim obtinuit, ut ut rem titulo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignatam nondum poſsideat. Novi quae fuerit illi conflata invidia; de illius nimirum in vera religione conſtantia dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant nonnulli, ſive ex animo ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve ſimulatè, Permagni autem intereſt Eccleſiae, eum qui re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquis praeeſſe debet, pietate eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am reliquos antecellere. Non dicam, quod dici ſanè poteſt, noſtrum non eſſe in religionem <hi>Principis</hi> inquirere: qualiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque ille fuerit, ſi poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem alioqui legitimam obtineat, ſi jus regnandi ad illum pertine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, caetera committenda ſunt divinae povidentiae, regi verò in rebus civilibus praeſtandum obſequium. Pontifici <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:112218:17"/> lubeat, Reges è ſolio de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urbare, niſi ad illius nutum res religionis componant, nobis non licet eſſe tam ſuperbis. Quae Dei ſunt Deo, quae Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaris ſunt Coeſari reddimus. Sed jam hoc totum omitto, ete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim quod rei caput eſt, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps ille in vera religione natus, ritè inſtitutus ab ejus publica profeſsione nunquam deſtitit, nè in eis quidem locis in quibus inde aliquid detrimenti captu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus videbatur, nec coetibus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris ſacris <hi>Rothomagi</hi> &amp; <hi>Rugallae</hi> dedignatus eſt intereſſe; Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terùm pietatis opinionem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet apud ſuos. Nunquam (fateor) Eccleſiamnoſtram prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentia ſua decoravit, dum <hi>Lute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae</hi> ſedem ſuam collocaverat, quod profectò nos malè habuit; verùm quia Presbyteranorum, quos vocant, cauſa ad nos vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur pertinere, qui Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rani
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:112218:17"/> ſumus, &amp; quia defun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti Regis mors Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranis aſcribebatur, alienum à nobis animum non potu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it non habere, uſque dum rerum eventus certiorem illum fecerint, non à Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribus noſtris, ſed ab Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtis ut plurimùm, aut ſaltem ab Independentibus illius inaugurationi praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pua inferri impedimenta, quos etiam calamitoſum Parentis fatum promoviſſe anteà, planè perſpectum habuit. Utinam facti iſtius invidia, quâ tandiu Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae noſtrae conflagrarunt tandem aliquando, &amp; à no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, &amp; à Fratribus <hi>Britan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi> prorſus amoveatur, quod neſcio an unqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turum ſit, niſi rebus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitis Filius ſceptrum Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentis gerat, à Presbytera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:112218:18"/> manibus non vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenter extortum, ſed amicè ac liberaliter oblatum. Age igitur, Vir Dei, belli imminentis calamitates praeverte, conſilia Pacis Túque Fratréſque tui ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miles inite, &amp; date <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannis.</hi> Aſpirabit divina providentia, conatibus veſtris benedicet, vobiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que utetur veluti ſacris inſtrumentis, ad foeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatem Patriae veſtrae re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituendam. Verùm haec ſatis ſupérque. Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris etenim quòd te adeò familiariter compellam, quae tamen me cauſa impulerit, dixi initio. Nempe tuâ Pietate, tuâ Charitate fretus, quae omnia meliorem in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem interpretabitur. Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò benedicat Deus ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diis
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:112218:18"/> tuis, laboribus tuis, Eccleſiae tuae, &amp; toti ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae, imò noſtrae, <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanniae,</hi> quae Flos eſt &amp; Gloria Regnorum in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Deus purè coli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Lutetiae Pariſ.</hi> Non. <date>April. An. 1660.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:112218:13"/>
               <head>RAIMOND GACHES Paſtor of the Reformed Church of <hi>Paris,</hi> to the moſt Famous man and moſt Upright Paſtor, <hi>RICHARD BAXTER,</hi> Wiſheth all Health.</head>
               <p>THough I am neither by face nor fame known unto you, (moſt worthy Sir, and moſt reverend brother in Chriſt) yet I addreſs my ſelf to you with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, becauſe I know you very well, and am fully aſſured of your Piety. <hi>I</hi> have read again and again, not without admiration, thoſe learned volumes (little indeed if we reſpect the bulk, but exceeding precious, and througbly dyed with the trueſt tinctures of Chriſtianity) wherewith you have bleſt your own Countrey, and with which <hi>France</hi> hath not been altogether unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted. Who can ſeriouſly read,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112218:14"/> though but one leaf of them, and not perceive how you felt the breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo God's ſpirit, and were ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably raiſed up for theſe unhappy times, as one who may with ſtout courage and invincible arms un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake and curb outragious ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs. <hi>I</hi> ſolemnly profeſs, I never ſaw any thing ſtudied, and come from thoſe, commonly called <hi>The Ancient Fathers of the Church</hi> or from the Doctors of the latter times, which doth with equal ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs breath forth the Authors, and alſo kindle the Readers devotion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Thoſe things which you have al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ready put out concerning <hi>Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reſt, A Call to the Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, juſtification</hi> (in which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you leave the beaten rode a little you do it, as far as I can underſtand not without reaſon and Scripture) <hi>Infant-Baptiſm, Peace of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> &amp;c. do witneſs moſt clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly both what your learning is, and what your love of Religion. Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:112218:14"/> then may forbid me to pour forth my careful and doubtfull thoughts into the boſome of ſuch and ſo great a man, and to declare what runs in my mind concerning the ſad and fickle ſtate of your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth? Truly I am no pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er into other mens matters; and eſpecially as to yours, I have been ſo far from angerly thundring <hi>[Virulent Declaiming]</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, that I have thought it an unſpeakable fault to diſpute curiouſly of them. I will ſay more, I could not but hope well of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> for I was, and am ſtill of this opinion, that God hath reſerved to himſelf in <hi>England</hi> more Elect, and more godly men, then ever ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther flouriſhed of old, or can be ſhewn now in any Realm of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome. Let both fearfull brethren and furious enemies, judge your ſafety deſperate, and ask in their unbelief, Who will
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112218:15"/> give ſalvation to <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi> God will provide; there are not ten, not a thouſand juſt men, but entire Millions of godly men. I will hear what the Lord God will ſay, for he will ſpeak peace to his people. But becauſe the moſt high Ruler of the world (who can indeed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the intervening of means, both ſcatter the darkneſs, and call back the Light, yet nevertheleſs) wills not (for the moſt part) to put forth his power immediately; we ought (Reverend Sir) to lay toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our Studies, and all Counſels to eſtabliſh firmly the ſafety of <hi>Britain:</hi> I ſuppoſe its condition will be perpetually tottering, until the Government return into one mans hands <hi>(Monarchy)</hi> As the cuſtomes of Nations are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and their diſpoſitions va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, ſo their manners of Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning publick affaires are various;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:112218:15"/> they are not of the ſame mind. One people chooſes a popular Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and neither is, nor can be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed to be ruled by one man: Another people, being taken with the ſplendor of Nobility, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the madneſs of the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty, prefers Monarchy. Your Country of <hi>England</hi> hath been a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Kings for almoſt innumerable ages; neither do I know any Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy in the world more ancient. The ſame Sun ſhines upon the preſent Engliſh men; the aſpects of the ſtars, the quality of the ſoil hath the ſame influence upon their affections now as formerly: Who then can hope that either a Democracy or Ariſtocracy, will eaſily prevail in that Countrey wherein Monarchy hath taken ſuch deep rooting? But <hi>England</hi> (may ſome man ſay) hath already chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the form of Government, and that (as it ſeem'd) with common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; who then can deny that may
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112218:16"/> be commodiouſly done, which hath been done commodiouſly? I have a double anſwer hereto. Firſt, I will in like manner query, whether that change proved very happy for <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland?</hi> Truely, if Taxes and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſts be to be counted; they are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doubled, but increaſed beyond al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all meaſure. If the State of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be to be conſidered, what a common-ſewer of Hereſies is there! Who ever heard of Ranters, Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> under the King? Secondly, Suppoſe <hi>Britain</hi> hath been happy ſince the change, yet it was under the Government of One: What matter's the name? this one was a Protector, not a King, I grant; but he was one, and ſuch a one, as was neither un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull in the art of ruling, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved himſelf inferiour to a King in diſſolving Parliaments; and from his death, or at leaſt from the caſting out of his Son, <hi>England</hi> never was quiet; changes were continual: whom
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112218:16"/> yeſterday we reverenced, to day we loath; whom we ſwore fealty to but now, him ſoon after we damn with curſes. Shall that most noble Queen of <hi>Iſlands</hi> alwayes be ſo toſſed upon the waves? and ſhall no Halcyon fly thither which may calm your ſeas? Truely, I fear, you will never have peace aſcertained either againſt tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults at home, or the attempts of Enemies abroad, till he, who is the Grand-ſon of ſo many Kings, at length be reſtored to his Grand-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Throne; he hath every where by right of inheritance the title of King of <hi>Britain,</hi> though he yet poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs not the thing deſigned by the Title. I know what <hi>Odium</hi> hath been caſt upon him; ſome, whether re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally or counterfeitly, are diſſatisfied in his constancy to the true religion; and alledge, that it concerns the Church very much, that he who is to rule others, ſhould excell them in godlineſs. I will not anſwer (which
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:112218:17"/> truly may be ſaid) that it belongs not to us to enquire into the Princes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; Be he what he will, (if his power be otherwiſe lawfull, and the right of reigning belongs unto him) Obedience in civil matters muſt be performed to the King, and other matters muſt be committed unto Divine Providence. Let the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> luſt to juſtle Kings out of the Throne unleſs they order affairs of religion according to his Beck; We may not be ſo proud. We give unto God the things that are Gods, and to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars. But I paſs over all this; for (which is the thing chiefly to be conſidered) this Prince being born, and duly educated in the true Religion, never departed from the publick profeſsion of it; no, not even in thoſe places in which he was likly to ſuffer loſs thereby; neither did he diſdain to be preſent at our religious aſſembly at <hi>Roan</hi> and <hi>Rochel;</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:112218:17"/> moreover be hath the eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of godly uſe among thoſe that are about him. I confeſs he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver graced our Church with his preſence while he was ſeated at <hi>Paris;</hi> which truely grieved us: but becauſe the Caſe of thoſe called Presbyterians ſeemed to concern us who are Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians; and becauſe the Kings death was aſcribed to the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians; he could not but be ſtrange to us, untill the event of things certified him that his inſtalment was principally hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered not by our brethren, but by the Anabaptiſts for the moſt part, or at leaſt the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents: whom alſo he certainly underſtood to have before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted his Fathers ſad death. I wiſh the Odium of that fact, wherewith our Churches have ſo long been loaded, might now at length be removed both from
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:112218:18"/> us, and our Engliſh brethren: which I know not how it can e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be, unleſs matters may be ſo compoſed as the Sonne may bear his Fathers Scepter, not violently wreſted out of the Presbyterians hands but friendly &amp; freely proffer'd. Go on Reverend Sir; prevent the calanities of imminent warre; do you and the brethren like you embrace peaceable counſels, and give the like to your Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Divine providence will favour and bleſs your endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, and will uſe you as ſacred inſtruments for reſtoring hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to your Country. Bute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough and too much of this, for you may wonder that I ſpeak ſo familiarly to you; but I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the beginning what cauſe moved me thereto, viz. relying on your piety and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which will take all in good
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:112218:18"/> part. Further, God bleſs your Studies, your labours, your Church, and all your, nay our England, which is the Flower and Glory of all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes wherein God is truly worſhiped.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Paris <date>
                        <hi>Apr.</hi> 2. 1660.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="fre" type="version">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:112218:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>De</hi> PARIS <hi>ce</hi> 3. <hi>Auril</hi> 1660.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Monſuur &amp; tres-honoré Frere,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IL n'eſt rien arrivé en nos jours de plus étonnant que les Revolutions d'<hi>Angleterre,</hi> d'<hi>Ecoſſe,</hi> &amp; d <hi>Irlande.</hi> Apres la mort tragique du feu Roy, l'on faiſoit eſperer l'établiſſement d'une Republique qui ſeroit la merveille &amp; l'admiration du Monde. Maisles divers chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemens quiſont arrivés de tems en tems, &amp; les confuſions qui ſont a craindre, font croire a pluſieurs que Dieu veut rame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner les choſes a leur Principe, &amp; mettre ces trois Couronnes unies enſemble, ſur la teſted un ſeul Monarque. Ce qui nous réjouït &amp; nous conſole eſt, qu'il ſemble que pour faire ce glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eux ouvrage, Dieu ſe veuille
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:112218:19"/> ſervir de ceus avec leſquels nous auons une communion plus étroite de doctrine &amp; de diſcipline. Car nous appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons que ceus que l'on apelle Presbyteriens, ont aujourduy le plus de pouvoir, &amp; que ce ſont eus qui tie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nent le timon de l'Etat. Cette Illuſtre Aſſemblée qui vouloit conſerver a ſon Roy ſa vie &amp; ſa Royauté, étoit ſans doute bien éloignée de vouloir priver ſes enfans du du droit qui leur eſt aquis par une Succeſsion continuée en leur Maiſon Royale depuis pluſieurs ſiecles. Il court icy un bruit que ce qui pourroit empeſcher le Roy d'a preſent d'eſtre rapellê a l heritage de ſes Peres eſt l'opinion que l'on a qu'il eſt Catholique Romain, &amp; la crainte qu'avec le tems, il ne ruine la Religion qui fleurit dans les trois Royaumes. Mais
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:112218:20"/> Monſieur, vous ſavez que nous avons toûjours deteſté la do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine des Papes &amp; de leurs ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſts qui enſeignent que les Princes qu'ils apellent Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, ſont inhabiles a ſucceder aus Couronnes, &amp; que s'ils ſont en poſſeſsion du Royaume, ils doivent eſtre depoſez. Outre cela, je ne ſay pas ſur quoy l'on fonde que ce Prince eſt Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Romain, veu qu'il n'en fait point la profeſsion, et au contraire qu'il a refuſé tous les avantages &amp; toutes les aſsiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces qui luy ont été ofertes a cette condition. La charité n'eſt point ſoubçonneuſe; Et ſi elle nous defend de ſoub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccedil;onner le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerement des particuliers, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment pourroit elle approuver que l'on ſoup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccedil;onne des Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonnes ſi ſacrées. l'Experience a aſſéz fait voir combien ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent de tels ſoup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccedil;ons, &amp; même
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:112218:20"/> les plus violens, ſont mal fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dez. Nos Hiſtoires ont fait voir un exemple bien convain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant. Car la <hi>Ligue</hi> ne fonda jamais ſa rebellion contre le Roy <hi>Henry</hi> 3. que ſur ce qu'il étoit Heretique &amp; fauteur d' Heretiques; Et par là on vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loit faire croire qu'l n'avoit nulle affection a la Religion Romaine, &amp; que ſous main il favoriſoit la nôtre. Cependant nous n'avons point eu de plus puiſſant ennemy; et chacun ſait qu'il a vêcu &amp; qu'il eſt mort en la Communion de <hi>Rome;</hi> &amp; qu'il y a fait paroiſtre autant de zele qu'aucun de ſes Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuss; Mais ſans paſſer la Mer, vous aves au milieu de vous un exemple ſans repartie. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quels ſoup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccedil;ons n'a on point eu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de la Religion du feu Roy de la grande <hi>Bretagne?</hi> Cependant a l'heure que la diſsimulation
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:112218:21"/> n'a plus de lieu, &amp; qu'il n'avoit plus rien a eſperer ni a craindre de la part des hommes, il a fait paroître ſon Zele a la vraye Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; et même cette douceur &amp; cette patience admirable avec laquelle il a ſouſert le dernier ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice de la main de ſes propres ſujets, a bien fait voir que l Eſprit de Dieu regnoit en ſon coeur. Il eſt vray que je ne vous puis rien dire de mon chef de la Religion du Prince dont il s'a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git, parce que pour des conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations politiques il ne nous a point fait I honneur de venir en nos S<hi rend="sup">tes</hi> Aſſemblées a <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renton,</hi> qui eſt le ſeul lieu où nons pouvons en corps té<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moigner nos reſpects aus Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces étrangers de nôtre Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Pour ce qui eſt de moy en particulier, je ſuis trop peu de choſe pour entreprendre de vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiter un ſi grand Prince; Et c'eſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:112218:21"/> auſſy la raiſon pour laquelle je n'ay point eu l'honneur de voir M<hi rend="sup">R</hi> le Duc d <hi>Yorc.</hi> Mais com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me j'apris il y déja quelques an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nées, que M<hi rend="sup">R</hi> le Duc de <hi>Gloce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> avoit fait paroître ſa ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance a confondre les faus Docteurs qui le vouloyent ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duire, &amp; qu'il avoit eu aſſez de courage &amp; de generoſité pour reſiſter à la Reyne ſa Mere et a ceux qui ce vouloyent placer en la maiſon des Jeſuites. Je creus, veu ſa grande jeuneſſe, que je me pouvois donner l'ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neur de le voir ſans que cela peut être tiré à conſequence; &amp; je m'aquittay d'autant plus vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiers de ce devoir, que je ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccedil;eus que non ſeulement il l'auroit agreable, mais qu'il le deſiroit. le ne vous ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccedil;aurois exprimer combien je ſus ſatisfait de ce jeune Prince. Car outre la facon obligeante de laquelle il
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:112218:22"/> me receut, il me donna divers témoignages de ſa pieté &amp; de ſon zele. Il me ſouvient, qu'il me dit entr'autres choſes, que le feu Roy ſon Pere, peu avant ſa mort, luy avoit recommandê ces trois choſes, De ne changer iamais de Religion, d'obeïr a ſon Frere ainé, qui ſeroit ſon Roy, comme il euſt fait aluy même ſi Dieu l'euſt conſervé au Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dé, &amp; d'obeïr a la Reyne ſa Mere en toutes choſes, excepté en ce qui regarde la Religion. A quoyil ajoutoit, qu'en perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verant en la Religion il s'aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toit de ſon devoir envers Dieu, &amp; conſervoit le repos de ſa con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; mais qu'avec cela il obeiſſoit aux dernieres volontés du feu Royſon Pere &amp; execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toit les ordres du Roy ſon Frere, qui le rapelloit pres de ſa perſonne pour le tirer de la ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Ce diſcours qu'il fit de
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:112218:22"/> fort bonne grace, me confirma dans la creance que j'avois de la Religion du Roy defunt, &amp; me fit voir ce que je devois croire charitablement de celle du Roy ſon Fitz. Mais outre cela, il a en ſa Maiſon &amp; entre ſes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtiques des gentils-hommes de nôtre Religion &amp; de mes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciens amis, qui m'ont aſſuré a diverſes fois de la pieté de ce Prince, &amp; de ſa fermeté en la profeſsion qu'il fait. Il eſt vray qu'il y a des Anglois, qui ſans y penſer, luy ont fait grand tort Car ſur de faux prejugez, ils ſe ſont abſtenus de nôtre commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; E par là ils ont fait nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre des ſoup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccedil;ons, comme ſi leur Roy &amp; toute ſa Cour avoyent leur inclination au Papiſme. Mais les plus ſages n'en ont pas vſé de la ſorte. Car ſachant que la creance de nôtre Egliſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:112218:23"/> &amp; celle de l'Egliſe <hi>Anglicane</hi> eſt une même creance, il's n'ont fait nulle difficulté de ſe trouver en nos Aſſemblées; Et même le premier Chapelain du Roy de la grand' <hi>Bretagne,</hi> nomme le Docteur <hi>Coſin,</hi> y a ſouvent aſsiſté avec beacoup de devotion. Pour reuenir a mon diſcours Dieu met aujourduy entre les mains de Meſsieurs vos Presbyteriens, qui ont la ſouveraine direction, l'honneur &amp; la reputation de nos Egliſes. Car ſi ſans aucune interventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on des Puiſſances étrangeres, ils rappellent ce Prince &amp; le font aſſeoir ſur ſon trône, ils acquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent pour eux &amp; pour leur po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterité une gloire immortelle; Et ils ferment â jamais la bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che a ceux qui nous accuſent fauſſement d'eſtre ennemis de la Royauté; &amp; font voir que
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:112218:23"/> ceſt a tort que l'on nous a im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puté cette maxime, Point d'Eueſque, point de Roy. Pour ce qui eſt de ma per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonne, Je vous confeſſe, que comme j'ay pleuré amérement la mort ſanglante du feu Roy, auſſy ce me ſera une joye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tréme de voir le rétabliſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment du Roy ſon Fils, pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veu que cela ſe puiſſe faire avec des conditions qui n'éffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent point le luſtre &amp; l'eclat de la Majeſté Royale, &amp; qui ſoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent a la glorie de Dieu &amp; au bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en &amp; au repos des trois Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aumes. C'eſt dequoy je prie Dieu de bon coeur, &amp; pour vous M<hi rend="sup">R</hi> qu'ilvous conſerve &amp; vous beniſſe de ſes plus ſaintes benedictions. J'ay creu que vous ne trouveries pas mauvais que je vous ouvre mon coeur, et que je vous découvre mes pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſées
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:112218:24"/> ſur un ſujet de ſi grande importance, puis que je ſuis.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>MONSIEUR,</salute>
                  <signed> 
                     <hi>Vôtre tres humble frere &amp; tres-affectionné Serviteur,</hi> DRELINCOURT, <hi>Paſteur d'Egliſe de</hi> PARIS.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>A Monſieur Monſieur <hi>Stoupe</hi> f. M. D. S. E. <hi>A Londres.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:112218:19"/>
            <head>PARIS <hi>April</hi> the 3<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> 1660.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> My honoured Brother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Nothing hath happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more ſtrange in our daies, then the revolutions of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> After the tragicall death of the late King, hopes were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that a Common-wealth might be eſtabliſhed, that ſhould become the wonder and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the whole world. But the ſeverall changes that have happened ſince, from time to time, and the confuſions that are to be feared, cauſe many to believe, that God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce affaires to their firſt ſtate, and ſet the three Crownes u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited, upon the head of one Monarch. That which in this doth moſt rejoyce and comfort
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:112218:19"/> us: is, that it ſeems for the do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing of this glorious work, God will uſe the Service of thoſe with whom we have more ſtrict Communion in doctrine and diſcipline. For we underſtand, that ſuch as are called Presbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians, are now poſſeſſed of the greateſt Power, and ſit at the Helme of State. That illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Aſſembly which would have preſerved to their King his life, and his Royaltie was without doubt very farre from deſigning to rob his Children of that right which is convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them by a continued ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion in their Royall Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie for many ages. A report is here, that the thing from being recalled to the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of his Fathers, is, the Opinion conceived by ſome, of his being turned to the Roman
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:112218:20"/> Catholick Profeſsion, and the fear that in time he might ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine the Religion now flouriſhing in thoſe three Kingdoms. But Sir, you know that we have ever deteſted the doctrine of Popes and their Inſtruments, who teach that all Princes, called by them Hereticks, are inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of ſucceſsion of Crowns, and if in poſſeſsion, to be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out. And more then this, I ſee not any ground there is for calling this Prince a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick, he making no profeſsion of it; but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary hath rejected all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages and all the aides of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to him upon that conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Charity is not jealous, and if it forbid us to ſuſpect on ſlight grounds private perſons, how can it approve jealouſies upon Perſons ſo ſacred? Experience hath taught us how little reaſon
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:112218:20"/> hath in the end appeared, for the like, and even the greateſt apprehenſions of that kinde, our Hiſtory doth furniſh us with a convincing example. The <hi>League</hi> never pretended other cauſe for their rebellion againſt King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, but for his being an Heretick, and a maintamer of Hereticks. And thence was inferred, that he was no waies affected to the Roman, and a Favourer of our Religion. In the mean time, we never had a more potent Enemy; and to all mens know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge he lived and dyed in the Communion of <hi>Rome,</hi> and therein ſhewed as much zeal as any of his Predeceſſors. But not paſs the Seas, you have in the midſt of you an inſtance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all contradiction: For what jealouſies have not been raiſed againſt the Religion of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:112218:21"/> the late King of Great <hi>Britain,</hi> and yet at the hour when there was no place for diſſembling, as being void of feares and hopes from man, he made his zeale to the true Religion appear, and even that ſweetneſs and that admirable patience with which he ſuffered death by the hands of his own Subjects, hath made it very viſible that the Spirit of God reign'd in his heart. True it is that from my ſelf, I am not able to relate any thing touching the Religion of that Prince: Becauſe for rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of State, we had not the honour of his preſence in our Aſſemblies of <hi>Charenton,</hi> the only place where in a formall body wee are able to witneſs the reſpect we bear to ſtranger Princes in commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with us. And as to my ſelf, I am not conſiderable enough to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:112218:21"/> have made a viſite to ſo great a Prince, which was alſo the reaſon why I had not the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to ſee the Duke of <hi>York:</hi> But two year ſince being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formd, how the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> had manifeſted his ability to confound the falſe Doctors that had undertaken to ſeduce him, and that he had courage and generoſity enough to reſiſt thoſe who would have placed him in the Colledge of the Jeſuites: I thought conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering how very young he was, that I might have the honour to give him a viſite, without apprehending any diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. And I performed it the work freely becauſe: I knew that not only he would accept it, but did alſo deſire it. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expreſs how much I was ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with that young Prince. For beſides the obliging man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:112218:22"/> wherewith he receaved, and he gave me ſeverall proofs of his zeale and piety. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that among other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, he tould me, how the late King his Father, a little before his death, had charged him with three things.? Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to change his Religion, to obey his elder Brother, who was to be his King, in the ſame manner as he would have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed himſelf if God had ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his life. And to continue obedient to the Queen his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in all: but what related to Religion. To which he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that in perſevering in his Religion, he did not only do his duty towards God, and preſerve the peace of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; but alſo performe the laſt will of the King his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and follow the order of the King his Brother, who
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:112218:22"/> had ſent for him, to free him of future temptations. This diſcourſe which he delivered with a very good grace, confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me in the beliefe I had of the late Kings Religion, and made me ſee what I ought in charity to believe of the King his Son. But over and above there be in his family among his domeſticks, ſome gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of our Religion, and my auncient friends, who at ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall times have given me aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of the piety of this Prince, and his ſtability in the profeſsion he makes. True it is Engliſh men have unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly done him great wrong; for upon falſe prejudices they have ſtayed from Communion with us, and ſo have raiſed jealouſies, as if their King and all his Court, were inclined to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:112218:23"/> Popery: But the more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet behave themſelves other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, for knowing that the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of our Church, and that of that Church of England is the ſame they willingly came to our Churches and even Dr <hi>Coſin</hi> the King of Great <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain's</hi> Chapplain hath joyn'd with us with great devotion. To returne to my diſcourſe, God intruſts at this day your Presbyterians; the Gentlemen now in power with the honour and reputation of our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: For if without the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervening of any foraigne pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, they recall this Prince and ſeate him in his Throne, they acquire to them ſelves, and to their poſterity an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall glory, and ſtop their mouthes for ever: who charge us falſly as enemies of Royalty,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:112218:23"/> and make appear, that the Maxime, of no Biſhop no King is injuriouſly imputed to us. For my part I confeſs, that as I have deplored with bitter teares the bloody death of the late King: So ſhall it be to me an exceeding joy, to behold the reeſtabliſhment of the King his Son: if perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with circumſtances not leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſening the ſplendor of Royall Majeſty: And which may be to the glory of God, and the good and reſt of the three Kingdomes. 'Tis for this that I will offer up my hearty pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to God: and for you Sir, that he will preſerve and bleſs you. I have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded my ſelfe, that you would not take it ill that I open my heart to you, and diſcover my thoughts upon a
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:112218:24"/> ſubject of ſuch moment: ſince I am.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed> 
                  <hi>Your Moſt humble, and Moſt affectionate Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Servant,</hi> DRELINCOURT, <hi>Miniſter of the Church of</hi> PARIS.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>A Monſieur Monſieur <hi>Stroupe</hi> f. M. D. S. E. <hi>A Londres.</hi>
            </trailer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:112218:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
